Guide to the Burmese Archive collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Burmese Archive collection
1943-1945
MS 113
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
A collection of photocopies of approximately forty items dealing with Independent Burma, 1943-1945. The documents record the establishment of Independent Burma in August 1943 and continue with letters, memoranda and other papers dealing with the problems of continued Japanese occupation. The major figure is Dr. Ba Maw who was head of state in the Burmese government.
Bha Moʻ, 1893-1977
Immediate Source of Acquisition
In 1959 Dr. Ba Maw donated these papers to Yale University. In December 1965 he transferred them to the Burmese government; the collection now in Manuscripts and Archives is made up entirely of photostatic copies of the originals.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
A collection of photocopies of approximately forty items dealing with Independent Burma, 1943-1945. The documents record the establishment of Independent Burma in August 1943 and continue with letters, memoranda and other papers dealing with the problems of continued Japanese occupation. The major figure is Dr. Ba Maw who was head of state in the Burmese government.
The papers are arranged in chronological order. Items in both Japanese and Burmese are included, most of which are accompanied by English translations.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Burma; Asia; Burma -- History -- Japanese occupation, 1942-1945; Japan -- History -- 1926-1945; Hirohito, Emperor of Japan, 1901-1989; Bha Moʻ, 1893-1977; Htun, Aung U, 1893-; Ishii, Itarō, 1887-1954; Isomura, Takeaki; Kawabe, Masakazu, 1886-1965; Ōkōchi, Denshichi; Paing, U, 1907-; Sawada, Renzö, 1888-; Shigemitsu, Mamoru, 1887-1957; Tōjō, Hideki, 1884-1948
- Original accession
  - Tojo, Hideki: TLS to Ba Maw giving instructions for setting up the Burma Independence Preparatory Commission (Japanese and English versions), 1943 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Kawabe, Masakazu: - TLS to Burma Independence Preparatory Commission instructing that Independence be granted on August 1, 1943 (Japanese and English versions), 1943 July 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Treaty of alliance between Japan and Burma (Japanese and English versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Proclamation issued by the commander-in-chief of the Japanese army in Burma, terminating the administration of the Burmese government appointed by the Nippon Military Administration (Burmese and Japanese versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Proclamation issued by the commander-in-chief of the Japanese army in Burma, terminating the Nippon Military Administration (Burmese and Japanese), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Declaration of Independence (Burmese and English versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Constitution for Government of-Burma (Burmese and English versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Declaration of war against Britain and the United States (Burmese and English versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memorandum of agreement regarding Shan-Karenni States (Burmese and Japanese versions), 1943 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hirohito, emperor of Japan: telegram and TLS to Ba Maw appointing Henze Sawada as ambassador to Burma (Japanese and English versions), 1943 August 4 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum of understandings in regard to the administration of the frontier region occupied by Japanese forces in Burma with map showing regions to be administered by the Japanese army (Burmese and Japanese versions), 1943 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum regarding Japanese military counselors in Burma (Burmese and Japanese versions), 1943 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Paing, U: TL to district military commanders ordering cooperation with Japanese forces (Burmese version), 1943 September 3 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Treaty concerning Shan-Karenni-Wa States (Japanese, French and English versions), 1943 September 25 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memorandum of the secret understanding in regard to administration of the frontier region occupied by Japanese forces upon the annexation of the Shan-Karenni-Wa States by Burma, with map showing the frontier region under Nippon Military Adminstration (Burmese, Japanese, and-English versions), 1943 December 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Agreement between the Minister for Cooperation, Labor, and General Affairs and Major-General Takeaki Isomura on executing the transfer of the enemy properties (English version), 1944 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hirohito, emperor of Japan: TLS to Ba Maw recalling Renzo Sawada as Ambassador to Burma (Japanese and English versions), 1944 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hirohito, emperor of Japan: TLS to Ba Maw appointing Itaro Ishii as Ambassador to Burma (Japanese and English versions), 1944 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 8)